Guide to the Carrington Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Carrington Family papers
1749-1929
MS 130
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(8 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, pamphlets, printed material, scrapbooks, sermons, and other papers relating to members of the Carrington family. Henry Beebee Carrington (1824-1912) and his grandfather, David Lewis Beebe (1763-1803), are two central figures in the papers. Material relating to David Lewis Beebe, including essays and sermons, documents his religious duties in Connecticut and family concerns in Ohio. Henry Beebee Carrington material includes correspondence, a diary, a letterbook, maps, pamphlets, scrapbooks, and other items documenting his experiences as a student at Yale University, as a lawyer practicing in Ohio, and as a commanding officer for Union forces during the Civil War. Carrington's role in military campaigns and treaty negotiations with Indians of the American West is also documented. His design of Fort Philip Kearney, the site of a famous massacre, and treaty negotiations with the Flathead Indians of Montana are detailed in pamphlets, scrapbooks and other papers.
Carrington family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter Cook and the Carrington estate, 1942-1948.
Existence and Location of Copies
Correspondence, 1866-1912, is available on microfilm (585 frames on l reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM176.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, 1790-1929. II. Family Papers, 1749-1929.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, pamphlets, printed material, scrapbooks, sermons, and other papers relating to members of the Carrington family. Henry Beebee Carrington (1824-1912) and his grandfather, David Lewis Beebe (1763-1803), are two central figures in the papers. Material relating to David Lewis Beebe, including essays and sermons, document his religious duties in Connecticut and family concerns in Ohio. Henry Beebee Carrington material includes correspondence, a diary, a letterbook, maps, pamphlets, scrapbooks, and other items documenting his experiences as a student at Yale University, as a lawyer practicing in Ohio, and as a commanding officer for Union forces during the Civil War. Carrington's role in military campaigns and treaty negotiations with Indians of the American West is also documented. His design of Fort Philip Kearney, the site of a famous massacre, and treaty negotiations with the Flathead Indians of Montana are detailed in pamphlets, scrapbooks and other papers.
The Carrington Family Papers are arranged in two series:
I. Correspondence, 1790-1929
II. Family Papers, 1749-1929
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE, 1790-1929, contains correspondence of David Lewis Beebe (1790-1791) relating to his pastoral duties as minister for the First Society of Woodbridge, Connecticut. Henry Beebee Carrington correspondence begins in the 1840s with personal letters from George Rockwell and other friends at the Irving Institute in New York. Carrington's military career is documented by correspondence, telegrams, and copies of documents from the 1850s-1860s. This includes a letter from Salmon P. Chase which records Carrington's appointment as judge advocate general in Ohio. Daniel Wolsey Voorhees, a congressman (1861-1866; 1869-1873) and senator (1877-1897) from Indiana is represented through several letters he wrote in the 1860s. Voorhees argued against the constitutional aberrations of secession and military rule.
Additional correspondence concerns Carrington's military duties, including his efforts to recruit Union soldiers in Indiana, his opposition to the efforts of the Sons of Liberty, and the military courts he convened to carry out his duties. Correspondence subsequent to 1865 focuses on the Indian campaigns Carrington participated in, his establishment and command of Fort Philip Kearney, and his treaty negotiations with the Flathead Indians of Montana. Correspondence from the 1900s details Carrington's literary career as an author of American historical and military texts, including works on the American Revolution, the Civil War, and his own experiences in the American West. Selected correspondence is also available on microfilm (HM 176).
SERIES II, FAMILY PAPERS, 1749-1929, contains a variety of writings by Henry Beebee Carrington, including a composition entitled "Exodus of the Flatheads." A diary (1845-1849) provides extensive detail on Carrington's student years at Yale College and Yale Law School. In addition, maps, pamphlets, printed material, and scrapbooks detail the history of Fort Philip Kearney, the site of a well-known massacre and a fort built and established by Carrington.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Beebee Carrington was born in Wallingford, Connecticut on March 2, 1824. He graduated from Yale in 1845 (B.A.) and attended Yale Law School in 1847. He practiced law in Ohio. During the Civil War he was appointed colonel of the 18th U.S. Infantry (May, 1861) and brigadier general of volunteers (Nov, 1862). Carrington supervised military tribunals in Indiana and Ohio, trials later ruled "illegal" by the Supreme Court. He was mustered out of volunteer service in 1865. He joined his regiment in 1866 and established Fort Philip Kearney in the Dakota Territory. He led military campaigns against the Sioux Indians, negotiated a treaty with the Flathead Indians of Montana, and conducted relocation and census studies of other tribes. Carrington wrote several popular American history texts. He died in Hyde Park, Massachusetts on October 26, 1912.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Crow Indians; Education; Families; Fetterman Fight, Wyo., 1866; Indians of North America -- Missions; Indians of North America -- Montana; Salish Indians; Siouan Indians; Women; Connecticut; Middle West; New York (State); Ohio -- History; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Wallingford (Conn.) -- History; West (U.S.); Diaries; Clergy; Historians; Lawyers; Soldiers; Ainsworth, Fred C. (Fred Crayton), 1852-1934; Alger, R. A. (Russell Alexander), 1836-1907; Allison, William B. (William Boyd), 1829-1908; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916; Armstrong, S. C. (Samuel Chapman), 1839-1893; Augur, Christopher Columbus, 1821-1898; Badeau, Adam, 1831-1895; Bancroft, George, 1800-1891; Barton, James L. (James Levi), 1855-1936; Barton, William E. (William Eleazar), 1861-1930; Beebe, David Lewis, 1763-1803; Black, John Charles, 1839-1915; Bonaparte, Charles J. (Charles Joseph), 1851-1921; Boutwell, George S. (George Sewall), 1818-1905; Boynton, Henry V. (Henry Van), 1835-1905; Buckingham, William A. (William Alfred), 1804-1875; Burbridge, Stephen G. (Stephen Gano), 1831-1894; Burton, Theodore E. (Theodore Elijah), 1851-1929; Carrington, Henry B., 1824-1912; Cortelyou, George B. (George Bruce), 1862-1940; Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879; Chase, Salmon P. (Salmon Portland), 1808-1873; Colfax, Schuyler, 1823-1885; Conkling, Roscoe, 1829-1888; Coolidge, Susan, 1835-1905; Cox, Jacob D. (Jacob Dolson), 1828-1900; Cox, Samuel Sullivan, 1824-1889; Crook, George, 1829-1890; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892; Cuyler, Thomas Dewitt, 1854-1922; Dawes, Henry L. (Henry Laurens), 1816-1903; De Peyster, J. Watts (John Watts), 1821-1907; Dennison, William, 1815-1882; Derby, Edward Henry Stanley, Earl of, 1826-1893; Devens, Charles, 1820-1891; Dow, Neal, 1804-1897; Endicott, William Crowninshield, 1826-1900; Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901; Fairchild, Lucius, 1831-1896; Farney, John Wien, 1817-1881; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893; Franklin, William Buel, 1823-1903; Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881; Gordon, John Brown, 1832-1904; Grant, Frederick Dent, 1850-1912; Gresham, Walter Quintin, 1832-1895; Griffis, William Elliot, 1843-1928; Guild, Curtis, 1827-1911; Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856-1930; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909; Hancock, Winfield Scott, 1824-1886; Hawley, Joseph R. (Joseph Roswell), 1826-1905; Hay, John, 1838-1905; Hayes, Rutherford B., 1822-1893; Hazen, William Babcock, 1830-1887; Heintzelman, Samuel Peter, 1805-1880; Henderson, John B. (John Brooks), 1826-1913; Herford, Brooke, 1830-1903; Hilles, Charles Dewey, 1867-1949; Hitt, Robert R. (Robert Roberts), 1834-1906; Hoadly, George, 1826-1902; Hoar, George Frisbie, 1826-1904; Holt, Joseph, 1807-1894; Howard, O. O. (Oliver Otis), 1830-1909; Hughes, Thomas, 1822-1896; Ingalls, John James, 1833-1900; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859; Jesup, Morris K. (Morris Ketchum), 1830-1908; Lamont, Daniel Scott, 1851-1905; Lane, Henry Smith, 1811-1881; Lee, Fitzhugh, 1835-1905; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Lincoln, Robert Todd, 1843-1926; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924; Long, John Davis, 1838-1915; Lossing, Benson John, 1813-1891; Lowell, A. Lawrence (Abbott Lawrence), 1856-1943; Lyon, William Penn, 1822-1913; McClellan, George B. (George Brinton), 1826-1885; McDowell, Irvin, 1818-1885; Morgan, T. J. (Thomas Jefferson), 1839-1902; Morton, Oliver P. (Oliver Perry), 1823-1877; Munger, Theodore Thornton, 1830-1910; Noble, John W. (John Willcock), 1831-1912; O'Reilly, John Boyle, 1844-1890; Pendleton, George H. (George Hunt), 1825-1889; Phisterer, Frederick, 1836-1909; Porter, Fitz-John, 1822-1901; Prevost, George, Sir, 1804-1893; Proctor, Redfield, 1831-1908; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912; Rockwell, George, 1824-1912; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Rosecrans, William S. (William Starke), 1819-1898; Ryan, P. J. (Patrick John), 1831-1911; Sanborn, John B. (John Benjamin), 1826-1904; Schofield, John McAllister, 1831-1906; Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866; Sheridan, Philip Henry, 1831-1888; Sherman, John, 1823-1900; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891; Sherwood, Kate Brownlee, 1841-1914; Sickles, Daniel Edgar, 1819-1914; Sidell, William Henry, 1810-1873; Smith, Hoke, 1855-1931; Sprague, Kate Chase, 1840-1899; Sprague, William, 1830-1915; Stanbery, Henry, 1803-1881; Stanford, Leland, 1824-1893; Stanton, Edwin M. (Edwin McMasters), 1814-1869; Stevens, Benjamin Franklin, 1833-1902; Stone, Amasa, 1818-1883; Strong, Elnathan Ellsworth, 1832-1914; Taylor, John Phelps; Thompson, Richard W. (Richard Wigginton), 1809-1900; Thornton, Edward, Sir, 1817-1906; Tod, David, 1805-1868; Trumbull, Lyman, 1813-1896; Tupper, Charles, Sir, 1821-1915; Voorhees, Daniel W. (Daniel Wolsey), 1827-1897; Wallace, Lew, 1827-1905; Warner, Charles Dudley, 1829-1900; Warren, Francis E. (Francis Emroy), 1844-1929; Washburne, E. B. (Elihu Benjamin), 1816-1887; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915; Weitzel, G. (Godfrey), 1835-1884; Wilson, James Grant, 1832-1914; Winsor, Justin, 1831-1897; Winthrop, Robert C. (Robert Charles), 1809-1894; Woodford, Stewart L. (Stewart Lyndon), 1835-1913; Wool, John E. (John Ellis), 1784-1869; Woolsey, Theodore Dwight, 1801-1889; Wright, Horatio Gouverneur, 1820-1899; Carrington family; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 18th; First Church Society (Woodbridge, Conn.); Sons of Liberty (1864); Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1845; Yale University -- Students
- Correspondence, 1790-1929; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence arranged in chronological order. Selected correspondence is also available on microfilm (HM 176).
  - 1790-1791; 1801-1863 (Box 1, Folder 1-18)
  - 1864 January-June (Box 2, Folder 19-33)
  - 1864 July-1899 (Box 3, Folder 34-50)
  - 1900-1929, undated (Box 4, Folder 51-56)
- Family Papers, 1749-1929; Series II
  This series contains material arranged in alphabetical order by record type.
  - Autographs collected by Henry Beebee Carrington, Undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Compositions written by Henry Beebee Carrington
    - "Dedication of the Greenwood School, Hyde Park, Massachusetts", 1888 April 5 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - "Absaraka", Undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
      General
      A brief essay on Crow Indian traditions, language, lands, and their relations with Anglo-Americans and other Indian tribes. Carrington calls for the establishment of Absaraka, a Crow homeland.
    - Manuscript of "Exodus of the Flatheads" [probably post-1902], Undated (Box 5, Folder 59-61)
      A discussion of Anglo-American settlement of the trans-Mississippi West and white-Indian relations. Carrington focuses on the Flathead Indians of Montana, white encroachment on their lands in the Bitterroot Valley, their removal to other territory, and the key role he played in negotiations with them.
    - "Indian Campaign of 1866", Undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
      A description of the 1866 war with the Sioux Indians under the command of Chief Red Cloud, emphasizing Carrington's role. Includes mention of the Fetterman Fight and of Carrington's return to Connecticut.
    - "Hovey Rebellion Record, 1864-1865", Undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
      This appears to be a typed transcription of a list of field notes and orders received and given by Carrington when he commanded Union forces in the Civil War in Kentucky and Indiana.
    - "Wallingford, Connecticut, 75 Years Ago", Undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
      A speech Carrington delivered at the centennial anniversary of Meriden, Connecticut discussing early colonial life in Connecticut.
    - Photocopies of documents from Folder 62, Undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - "Origin and Brief Sketch of the 18th U.S. Infantry", Undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
      Account of the formation of the division and some of the action it saw in the Civil War in Kentucky and Illinois, and Indian wars in Montana and Wyoming in the 1860s.
    - "Sketch of the 18th U.S. Infantry", Undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
      An appendix to an official Army report that includes Carrington's official account of the Fort Phil Kearney Massacre.
    - "Report on the Flathead Indians of Montana", Undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
      A discussion of the 1880s negotiation and removal of the Flathead Indians and their relations with and acculturation to white society.
    - "Report of Service Among the Flathead Indians 1889-1890", 1890 January 29 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      An in-depth look at the negotiations and removal of the Flathead, with information on the appraisement and sale of particular landholdings.
    - Xerox copies of documents from folder 64, Undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - "My Old Ohio Home", Undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
      A reminiscence about Ohio society in the 1840s and 1850s.
    - "Washington Irving 40 Years Ago: A Remembrance" (Box 5, Folder 66)
      A personal and literary tribute to Washington Irving.
    - "Responsible Insanity", Undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
      A discussion of insanity as a legal defense.
    - "Sermon", Undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
      A philosophical discussion of American religious and political beliefs, emphasizing liberty and missionary obligations.
    - "Yale College Life", Undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
      A description of Carrington's life at Yale College 1841-1845. Discusses student life and the allure of military service.
  - Diary: Carrington, Henry Beebee, 1845-1849 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Land book: Ohio, 1804; 1818-1860 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Letterbook, 1862-1864 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Maps: Fort Philip Kearney; Fort Sedwick; Ohio, Undated (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Pamphlets, 1856-1922, undated (Box 6, Folder 71-73)
  - Pictures, Undated (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Printed material, 1866, 1885, 1904, 1929, undated (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Fort Philip Kearney massacre, 1866 (Box 7, Folder 77-78)
    - Trip to Great Britain and France, 1875 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Sermons, 1749, 1791-1818 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Sermons and essays written by David L. Beebee, Undated (Box 8, Folder 81-82)
  - Oversize materials (Box 9)